<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | Till Schneidereit]]></title>
  <link href="http://tschneidereit.github.io/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tschneidereit.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-04T06:33:22+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://tschneidereit.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Till Schneidereit]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Brendan's Success]]></title>
    <link href="http://tschneidereit.github.io/2014/04/03/on-brendans-success/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-03T23:13:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://tschneidereit.github.io/2014/04/03/on-brendans-success</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This Open Web thing? <a href="http://brendaneich.com/">Brendan Eich</a> spent the last 20 years helping to create, then save, then grow it. It might still exist in some meaningful form without him. It might not.</p>

<p>Brendan has stated his motivation for this work over and over again: to enable free speech. I&rsquo;m sure he likes it better when that speech agrees with his own opinions. I know that he sees not just the freedom of speech but, more to the point, ways to efficiently disseminate all speech as transcending his personal opinions on almost all topics.</p>

<p>He succeeded fantastically well: the web is more open and better at facilitating speech than any other medium in the history of mankind. It is, as the <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2014/04/eff-statement-mozilla-and-importance-open-internet">EFF put it</a> &ldquo;one of humanity&rsquo;s greatest accomplishments&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Without this accomplishment, it&rsquo;s highly unlikely that Twitter would exist &ndash; the communications platform that enables the quick formation of movements for a cause in a way that puts everything before it to shame.</p>

<p>Without this accomplishment, it&rsquo;s highly unlikely that OkCupid would exist &ndash; the dating platform that <a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/alltechconsidered/2014/03/31/297342868/the-new-mozilla-ceos-political-past-is-imperiling-his-present">&ldquo;devoted the last ten years to bringing people—all people—together&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<p>Without this accomplishment, it&rsquo;s highly unlikely Brendan would have resigned today.</p>

<p>To the extend that his resignation is a victory for the LGBTQ movement, it is a victory that Brendan played a key role in enabling.</p>

<p>Unquestionably, it is an impressive demonstration of the Open Web&rsquo;s power. On his role in creating it, I want to congratulate Brendan, and thank him.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
